<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The dysclosyng of the canon of ye popysh masse with a sermon annexed vnto it of ye famous clerke of worthy memorye. D Marten Luther.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07229</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17626</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103743</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839488</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839488</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3915</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07229)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3915)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 56:14,)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The dysclosyng of the canon of ye popysh masse with a sermon annexed vnto it of ye famous clerke of worthy memorye. D Marten Luther.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[23] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprynted haue at al by me Hans hitpricke, [for] W. Copland?,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1548?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C(-C8).</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from colophon; publisher's name and publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Caption title on B2r (signed B3) reads: A sermon made bi the famous clerke of worthy memorye, Doctour Marten Luther of the great blasphemy agaynst God whych the Papystes daylie to vse reading thys Antech[r]istian canon  yn theyr masse.</note>
                  <note>Some print faded and show-through; some leaves stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Luther, Martin, 1483-1546 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Mass --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3915:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3915:1"/>
            <p> The dyſclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng of the Canon of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> popyſh Maſſe, with a ſermon annexed vnto it of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> famous Clerke of worthy memorye. D Marten Luther.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Apocal, xviii.</bibl>
               <p>Come away frome hyr my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that ye be not partakers in her ſynnes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye receiue not of her plages</p>
            </q>
            <p>All honour, prayſe, and glorye, be geuen onely to god</p>
            <p rend="centerJustify">
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>☞<g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>☞<g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               <lb/>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>☞<g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               <lb/>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               <lb/>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3915:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3915:2"/>
            <head>¶ To the Reader</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>rom the begi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nyg <note place="margin">Geneſ. i,</note> or at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt entra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>unce after the cee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>acio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> good chryſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reader God in hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe <note place="margin">Iohan, ii,</note> for ſeynge the way warde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of mannes harte, and how prone and readye it was, vnto wyckednes, and howe, ablyuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of the benefytes that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued of hys lorde Gods han<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> de <note place="margin">Eſal, i,</note> became not thankefull vnto hys myghty God, But vanyſ, <note place="margin">Roman, ii,</note> ſhed in the Imagynacyons of <note place="margin">Ieremy, iii<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> hys froward ſtomake, and wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhipped the workeman ſhyp of the handes of a caranous car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas ſubdued to all vanyte and forgat hys creatour, the whych <note place="margin">Exod, xxiii,</note> vngentelnes hathe bene of all other vyces, mooſte earneſtlye
<pb facs="tcp:3915:3"/> reprehended by the, mouthe of God euen from the beginni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, and not onelye reprehended but alſo wyth ſharpe threates and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynacyons, of hys mooſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred woorde appoynted to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <note place="margin">Roman, i.</note> dampnacion Beſides that he gaue them vp to theyr har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes <note place="margin">Deut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iii</note> luſte and plaged them with ſwearde, famyne and peſtilence Therfore good chryſten reder, lyfte vp thyne eyes and behold <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. Iohan, ii,</note> the abhomynacion of Idolatri <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Theſſ ii,</note> ſo ſhamefullye vſed in theſe da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yes of our tyme and not onelye vſed but with force and mayne <note place="margin">Pſalm, ii</note> fortefyed and vpholden wyth fyre and faggot crudelytye and ſtrength, and that ſoſore vphol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den <note place="margin">Math. xv,</note> that the eternall worde of God is clerely banyſſhed exiled and put too bed Howe ſayſte y<hi rend="sup">u</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3915:3"/> to this deteſtable and among al other the mooſt ſhameful maſe <note place="margin">S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, xii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and gaſyng ſtocke the wyckede maſſe the vpſprynge of Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the inuencyon of the deuyll the fayre frute of the Romiſh raue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng, <note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>el. ix.</note> Antechryſte and the lader hous of al his ſhauen poſteritie <note place="margin">Hier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>my, xv</note> Beholde it and abhorte it or el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les take it for a warnyng. God wyll abhorte the and caſt the in to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> lak that burneth with fyre and brimſtone wherfore I harte <note place="margin">Apocal. xx.</note> lye beſeche the; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all brotherly affeccyon, marke in thys lytell <note place="margin">phyli. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</note> volume or fewe lynes the tayle of the Dragon, of Gog and ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gog. the waſters of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore flock <note place="margin">Ezechiel xx<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. viii</note> of Chryſte the maynteyners of myſchefe the ſtudyers of ſuper ſticyon the fortefyers of
<pb facs="tcp:3915:4"/> of the malignaunt Chyrche the <note place="margin">Pſalm, xxvi</note> gylders of the tryple, Crowne / and thou ſhalte playnlye par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue <note place="margin">Coloſſ. ii</note> in an hondreth wordes. the ſhamefull legerdemayne &amp; craftie Iuggli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g that coſt them <note place="margin">Math. xiii,</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtudy not of a fewe hondreth years, and the ſweate of manye browes, for the whych bothe their pot and ſpytte, walke the merielier, vnto thys houre, It <note place="margin">Exod, xvi</note> is cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed the Canon of the myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheff a (of the Maſſe I woulde ſaye) that is to ſay the rule and order that they haue taken to fynyſh theyr ſlayne ſacryfyce, &amp; too brynge it to an ende. But what turmoylyng, ſtrugglynge w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſtlynge quid pro quo. wyth <note place="margin">Cor, xi.</note> my wayes is beſt hold thy han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de fro my throte there was tyll they had broughte it to the myſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhapen
<pb facs="tcp:3915:4"/> for me, that it is nowe in Polidorus Virgilius dothe <note place="margin">Lib, v, ca, x,</note> plainlye manyfeſt. Whervnto alſo y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> haſt a ſermon a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nexed, of the famous Clerke &amp; diſcloſer of the Popes Iuggling box &amp; of worthi memorye D. Martin Luther. Reade it I pray y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ſober Iudgement and conferte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Idolatries of the old time w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the obhominable Idolatry, in our tyme after the comming of Chryſte the pure and true light and y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt ſe it farre paſſe. Oh <note place="margin">Math, vi</note> moſt mighty father for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> tender loue that thou bareſt to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole <note place="margin">Iohn, iii.</note> world in that thou delyueredeſt thyne onely and ſwete ſonne Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus <note place="margin">Hebr, x,</note> Chryſt that holy and ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ent <note place="margin">Math, xxi,</note> ſacryfice, for the lyfe of the whole world Haue mercy vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs &amp; deliuer vs from y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſnares
<pb facs="tcp:3915:5"/> of Sathan, and from the dyue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyſh yock of this deteſtable I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrye and open the eyes of <note place="margin">Pſalm. xlv,</note> oure. Magyſtrates that they may proſperouſly fortefye they <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, iiii,</note> bleſſed woorde, as they haue be gonne graciouſly and to deface the bloudye kyndume of Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt <note place="margin">Apocal, xviii</note> and ſend the communalte obedye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſtomackes and hartes <note place="margin">Roma, xiii</note> to fortefi theyr Prynces quarel in all godlynes and ryght And that all chryſten reames, maye accorde in peace and vnyte and ſo to be incorporate in the miſty <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imoth, ii,</note> call body of God all myghte, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> whoſe head is chryſte Ieſus to whome I commyt the w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the encreaſe of hys knowledge. Amen.</p>
            <closer>Reade and then Iudge</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:3915:5"/>
            <head>The dyſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>loſyng.</head>
            <p>WE humblye pray and beſech the mooſt gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyous father, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou accept. <note n="a" place="margin">he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> eſt kyſſeth Aulter, an then make<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> iii, croſſes</note>. and bleſſe theſe giftes theſe rewardes the ſe holy vntaſted ſacryfyces. cheyfly which we offer vnto the for thy holy catholyke chyrche y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> thou mighteſt vouchafe to paci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fi kepe ſet to gither and gouern yt through the whol world with thy ſeruant our pope and name hym and our biſſhope named &amp; our king named &amp; with al fayth ful men &amp; louers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> catholike and apoſtolike fayth <note n="b" place="margin">here he ayeth fol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lyuyng <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>th no w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> prayeth</note> Remen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bre lord thy ſeruauntes menn &amp; women, he nameth whome he wyll and all that ſtand here ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, whoſe ſayth and deuocyon is knowen to the for whom we offer or themſelues offer
<pb facs="tcp:3915:6"/> this ſacrifice of prayſe for them and theyrs for redempcyon of cheyr ſoules, for hope of theyr owne health and proſperitye, &amp; paye theyr vowes to the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall lyuynge and true God, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng parte, and worſhyppynge the remembraunce ſpeciallye, of the gloryous and perpetuall vyrgin Mary, mother, of oure God and lorde Ieſus, Chryſte, yea and of thy bleſſed Apoſtles and Martyrs, alſo, as Peter, Paule, Andrew, Iames, Iohn Thomas. Iames Phylip Bar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tholome. Mathye Symon and Iude Lyne. Clete. Clement, Syxt. Cornele. Cipran. Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens. Gryſogon. Iohn &amp; Pauil Couſmas and damia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and of al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy Sayntes, through, whoſe merytes and prayers, graune,
<pb facs="tcp:3915:6"/> thou that we may in al thinges be defended by the helpe of thy protection by the ſame Chryſte oure lorde Amen</p>
            <p>We beſeche the therfore-O lorde, to bee pacyfyed, and to acceptthys oblacyon. <note n="c" place="margin">here he lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth on th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hoſte wyth great deuo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on</note>. of oure bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den dutie, yea &amp; of thy hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold alſo and to dyſpoſe oure dayes in thy peace and graunt that we maye be delyuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eternall dampnacion and bee nombred in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> flock of thin elect, through Chriſt our lorde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Amen</p>
            <p>Whych oblacion. <note n="d" place="margin">here <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> muſt loke it agayne</note> vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe thou God almyghty. to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke throughly we beſeche y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <note n="e" place="margin">here he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth, v, tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes</note>. the appointed ratefyede &amp; acceptable y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it maye be made to vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> body &amp; bloude of thy de reſonne Ieſus Chriſte <note n="f" place="margin">Here ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ioy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther wyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lyfteth v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hys ſacri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſayt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> who y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day before he ſuffred take bread in his holy &amp; worſhipful ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des
<pb facs="tcp:3915:7"/> and lifted vp hys eyes in to he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. <note n="g" place="margin">he caſteth by hys eyse</note>, to the God hys father al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myghtie, he gaue thankes to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> and bleſſed it brake it and gaue it to hys dyſciples ſaying take and eate of thys all for thys is my bodye.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="h" place="margin">he maketh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſaunce, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd euen lyf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth it vp o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er his head</note>. In lyke manner after ſupper was done, he tooke thys noble cuppe in his holy and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full handes and gaue thankes to the <note n="i" place="margin">he maketh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</note> and bleſſed <note n="k" place="margin">he croſeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s</note> and gaue hys dyſcyples ſayinge take ye. and drynke of it all <note n="l" place="margin">he lyfteth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, chalyce, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y a lytl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> for thys is the cuppe of my bloude of the newe Teſtament the myſtery of fayth whych ſhalbe ſhed for you and for many for the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyon of ſynnes. <note n="m" place="margin">he lyfteth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chalyce <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uer his hed</note> As often as euer ye do thys ye ſhall do it in the remembraunce of me wherby both we thy ſeruances
<pb facs="tcp:3915:7"/> remembre Lorde, and ſo do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thy holye people remembre the ſame Chryſt thy ſonne our lord God, as well his bleſſed paſſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on as his reſurrection yea and alſo his glorious aſcencion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to heauen and offer to thy no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Mateſſie of thy preſentes and gyftes a pure <note n="n" place="margin">he croſſeth his great, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſacrefyce a holy ſacrifyce and vnſpotted, ſactifise the holye breade of. e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall lyfe and the Cuppe of euerlaſſyng ſaluacyon. Ouer whyche vouchſafe thou toloke wyth a mexcyfull and cleare countenaunce. and accept it, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as thou dydeſt vouchſafe too accept<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the preſentes of thy ſeruaunte iuſte Abell, and the ſacrefyce of oure hyghe father Abraham and that whyche thy hyghe preeſſ Melchiſededh of: fred
<pb facs="tcp:3915:8"/> a holye ſacrifice, an vnſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted hoſte. We humblye deſyre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> almighti God commaund theſe thynges to be borne by the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of thy holy Angell into thy Aulter aboue, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyght of thy Godly Maieſtie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as many of vs as haue taken parte of thys Aulter, and haue receyued the holy halowed body and bloude of thy ſonne may be replenyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed <note n="o" place="margin">he croſſeth his face,</note> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all heuenly bleſſynge and grace thorugh the ſame Chryſte oure lorde Amen</p>
            <p>Remèbre alſo lorde thy ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes men N &amp; women N wbich are gone before vs <note n="p" place="margin">he prayeth for the dead &amp; ſpeketh ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer a worde but remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth whom he lyſte,</note> with thes ſygne of fayth and ſlepe in the ſlepe of peace we beſethe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord to pardonne them and all that reſt in Chriſte. and geue them a place of refreſſhing light and
<pb facs="tcp:3915:8"/> reſt through the ſame. Chryſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our lorde Amen</p>
            <p>To vs thy ſeruantes alſo <note place="margin">he knocketh hym ſelfe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the breſt</note> hopyng to the multitude of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mercies vouchſafe to geue ſom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me parte and fele ſhyppe wyth thy holye Apoſtles &amp; Martyr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Iohan. Stephen. Mathya<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Barnabas. Ignacyus. Alexan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elline. Peter. Felycy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas. Perpetua. Agatha. Lucye. Agnes. Cecylye, Anaſtalicus. &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all thy ſeints amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g whoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pany we beſech y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> admyt vs not eſtemi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g our deſeruyng but by y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> graunt of thy pardon throughe Chryſte our lord. <note n="r" place="margin">heuen i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, not ſpoken here</note> By whome O lorde all theſe good thynges <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all wayſe createſt ſanctyfyeſte quickneſt bleſſeſte and Gyuyſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to vs. <note n="s" place="margin">he bleſſeth the Chalyc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</note> By hym and wythe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ym &amp; in hym be to the God the
<pb facs="tcp:3915:9"/> father almyghty in the vnytye of the holy gooſt al honour and glory. ii. for euer woorlde with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out <note n="t" place="margin">he ſpeketh alowd</note> ende. x. Amen We beynge warnede by wholſome precep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and infourmede by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitucion of God dare bodelye ſay. <note n="v" place="margin">the clerke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſwereth,</note>. Our father ſhhyche arte <note n="x" place="margin">he holdeth vp, his han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des.</note> in heauen holowed be they na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. Thy kyngdome come. Thy wyll be done in earth, as hy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is in heauen. Gyue vs thys daye our daylye breade And forgyue vs our treſpaſſes as we fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that treſpaſſe agynſt vs, And let vs not be led in to temp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>acyon. <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, the preeſte ſayth ſecret<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye</note> x: But delyuer vs from euell. <note n="y" place="margin">the clerke ſayth</note> Amen. Delyuer vs, Lorde, we beſeche the, freme al euylles paſt preſent and for to, come and by the interceſſyon of the bleſſed and gloryous perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual
<pb facs="tcp:3915:9"/> virgin Marye the mother of god and thy blſſed Apoſtles Peter and Paule and Andrew with all thy Sayntes <note n="z" place="margin">He kiſſeth the pate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> putteth it to his right eye then he cro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his cron and layeth it doune agayn</note> be me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ifull and gyue peace in our da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yes that we being holpen by the helpe of thy mercy may be alwa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es bothe fre from ſyne and ſafe from <note n="ꝯ" place="margin">He breketh the H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſte in to, in, partes fyrſt in, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eng Amen</note> al trouble &amp; by the ſame o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ur lord Ieſus chriſt thy ſonne <note n="A" place="margin">Here he maketh it in iii, peces</note> which with the liueth and reing<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth in the vnytye of the holye ghooſte <note n="B" place="margin">He ſpek<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth allowde,</note> for euer and euer <note n="C" place="margin">The clerk ſayth</note> Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> The peace of <note n="D" place="margin">He croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, iii, times with on pec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Hoſt</note> the lord be euer wyth you O lambe of god which takeſt a way the ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne of the world haue mercy on vs O la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be of god whych takeſt away y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſinne of the world haue mercy on vs. O lambe of God which takeſt away the ſynne of
<pb facs="tcp:3915:10"/> he world gaue vs peace <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, he croſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth thee cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> with one pec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> hoſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chaly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Thys holy menglyng to ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther of the body &amp; bloud of oure Lorde Ieſus Chryſt be to me &amp; to all that receaue it, ſaluacyon of mynde and body and a heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th full preparacyon to deſerue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and receaue euerlaſtynge lyfe, trough y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame Chryſt our lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Amen</p>
            <p>O holy lord father almygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty eternall, God, graunt me to receaue this holy body &amp; bloud of thy ſoone our Lorde Ieſus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Chriſt ſo worthily that. I may deſerue by hyt to receue remyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon of all my ſinnes &amp; to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy holy ſpirit and to haue thy peace for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> act god alone &amp; there is none other but y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> whoſe kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; impe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> laſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> gloryous, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out ende foreuer
<pb facs="tcp:3915:10"/> &amp; euer Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <note n="F" place="margin">he M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>th the pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Peace be to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> &amp; to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church of God, <note n="G" place="margin">The cler<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſayth</note> &amp; to thy ſpyryte</p>
            <p>O God the father fountayn &amp; beginning of al gooons why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch by mercye wereſt ledde, and wouldeſt that thyne onelye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Sonne, ſhoulde comme doune too, the loweſte partes of the woorlde and take fleſhe which I vnwoorthy holde here in my handes <note n="H" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th downe to the Hoſte</note> I worſhipe the I gloryfy y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>, yea w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>all thinte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of my hart I prayſe the &amp; beſeche the that thou forſake not vs thy ſeruauntes but forgyuethe oure ſynnes, ſo that wee Maye bee able too, ſerue the, the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye lyuynge and trewe GOD, wyth apure harte and a chaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e boddye Thorouhe the ſame Ieſus Chryſt our lorde, Amen
<pb facs="tcp:3915:11"/> Let the obſeruaunce of my ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyce <note n="I" place="margin">After th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is colet he maketh a cr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſſe on the Aulter, kyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it &amp; put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tethe of hys vpper veſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> pleaſe the O holy trynyty and graunt that thys ſacryfyce whych I vnworthy haue offred to the eyes of thy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Maiſte maye be acceptable to the and propy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyatorye to me and to al them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue offred it for through th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mercy which liueſt and reigneſt god worl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de wyth out ende amen</p>
            <trailer rend="centerJustify">
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               <lb/>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>¶☞☞
<lb/>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>☞<g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               <lb/>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               <lb/>☞</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:3915:11"/>
            <head>A ſermon ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de bi the famous Clerke of wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy memorye, Doctour Marte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Luther of the great blaſphemy agaynſt God whych the Papyſtes daylie do vſe reading thys Antechriſtian canon yn theyr Maſſe</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore we take on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o vew or ſuruei y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> horible abhomina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion, <note place="margin">Danil. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</note> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt fyl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thi I dolatti aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſte <note place="margin">i, Ihon, ii,</note> God, of the mooſte curſed Canon which the ſluggiſhe pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyſtes call the maſſe in whyche they wyth cruell mouth daylye beſlauer the hygh Maieſtye of God. we thynke it beſt, that we
<pb facs="tcp:3915:12"/> laye the fundacyon of the truth and in fewe wordes to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d what the entraunce, &amp; ſtate of oure faythe is &amp; of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel alſo That is it conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pneth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vs and promyſyth ſaluacion by none other thyng but by Chryſt no though all the workes in the worlde were got into one heape for he is out ſaluacyon whyche <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> alſo gaue him ſelfe for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſynnes of the world and ſo reconſylyd vs to hys father whome is wel <note place="margin">Math <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> pleaſed in this Chryſte alone, &amp; forgeueth y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſynnes of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are grafted in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> body of Chryſt &amp; y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> by fayth alone to ſuche only I ſaye the father i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>puteth no ſynne for Chryſtes ſake. Now he that wil obteine forgiuenes of ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes committed by any other meane as by hoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, ſhauen crownes
<pb facs="tcp:3915:12"/> pylgrymages, bulles praers, <note place="margin">Iohn. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> faſtynges, foundacyons &amp;c. he is a theefe and a robber yea he putteth Chryſt to epproby &amp; ſha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me as though he weare an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mete and vnſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t redemer &amp; of none effect. &amp; was in vayne. ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged on y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> croſſe, &amp; ſlayne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo ſhamefull punyſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, But yet whatſoeuer he be, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truſteth to his owne worckes be it neuer ſo lytle he tredeth the precyous bloude of our redemer Ieſus Chryſt vnder foote, &amp; ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyeth God as though Chryſte were nothyng in fauour w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the father It muſt be knowen ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> no ſacryfyce is nowe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſight of the father but Chryſt onely whiche offred hym ſelf to him for vs ones for all and euer, &amp; by that dede, he
<pb facs="tcp:3915:13"/> ſwalowed vp the ſynnes of the holye worlde and made vs ſafe frome death hell and y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> deuell ſo that after that there neded no ſacryfyce at all to be offred too hym. For lyke as he was ſence that tyme no more bonde to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ath ſo lyke wyſe is it impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for hym to be offred annye more For not<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing can be made a ſacryfyce excepte it be ſlayne. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the myſerable papyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes make them ſelues readye to offer Chryſte they begynne too ſtrangle Chryſt and hang hym agayne as farre as in them ly, eth Howe foule an abhomina,+cyon it is we ſhal ſhew by theyr Canon. True it is in dede that y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Appoſtles and Prophetes ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>horte vs too offer ſacryfyce too God but not to offer chryſte
<pb facs="tcp:3915:13"/> but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mortifing of thold Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <note place="margin">i, Petri, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit our ſelues wholy to god This is y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſacrifice whyche <note place="margin">Oſe. iiii</note> god requyreth of vs and alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we prayſe &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out fea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re Seyng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is thus it muſt nedes follow y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what ſacryfyce ſoeuer be found out other then this, it is falſe &amp; blaſphemous We ſhal therfore try out theyr canon which wyll make you to be amaſed at y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> abhominacions that light hidden in it wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h, yet they make to be of more, value then the Goſpell. Thus begyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth the canon.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="canon">
               <body>
                  <head>The begynnyng of the canon,</head>
                  <p>We humbly praye and be ſeche the moſt gracious father that thou accept ad bleſſe theſe gyftes theſe rewardes
<pb facs="tcp:3915:14"/> theſe holye vntaſted ſacryfices</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>See ye what blaſphemy he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re is euen in the beginning of it Here ſtandeth a wretched brayn leaſe man at an Aulter, &amp; (lyke a fole) prayeth y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> he maye make an acceptable a holy and vntou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched ſacryfyce, where he hathe nothyng but a morſell of bread and a ſyp of wyne. Try yt wel for gods ſake how thes words ſtynke of a lye euen at the fyrſt If it be holye) marke well the wordes (with whatte mouthe, then prayeth he, that he maye now obteyne to make yt holye? Dareſt thou, O manne ſynfull and worms meat ſtand fourth in the ſyght of Goddes Maieſ,+tye, and before hym playe the
<pb facs="tcp:3915:14"/> foole thus w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a pece of bread / a litle wyne it followeth agayn</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="canon">
               <body>
                  <head>The canon</head>
                  <p>Chefely whych we offer vnto y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> for thy holye. Catholyk churc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that thou myghteſt / vouchſaf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to pacefye, keepe, ſettogyther &amp; gouerne it, through the whol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> worde, wyth thy ſeruaunt oure Pope. N and our Byſſhop. N, and our Kyng N and ſo fourth</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Oh thou varlette worſe thenne noughte: Dareſte / thou take vppon the, yea wyth what face dareſte thou ſo moche as ones thynke to offer that Lytell mor ſell of breade, and a Cuppe wy:+th al lytle wyne for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> catholyke
<pb facs="tcp:3915:15"/> Churche Oh good god howe thou arte defyed here. It we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re no Wonder to ſee a mannes harte ryue a ſonder too ſee the Deuell Alas the tyme howe he reigneth in the worlde. In thys place trewlye chryſte is vtterlye denyed when one ſhall ſay here is ready breade and wynne, and wythe thys we ſhall help all the whole worlde as he myght ſaye Thuſh father thou arte a foole and thy ſonne alſo we papyſtes ſhall nowe make a laufull ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyce whyche thou canſt not be a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gaynſte And as for thy ſone, he maye goo playe hym as one of noe force nor effecte Alas it wou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lde make a man too wepe that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloud ſhoulde braſte out at his eyes</p>
            <p>I thyncke verelye that the very
<pb facs="tcp:3915:15"/> ry Deuell hym ſelfe made th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ys Canone. For howe coulde, there elles bee made any greter thynge to dyſhonour God. aga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yne, thys goodlye why pſter b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geth people wyth hym to make an oblacyon too God. yea and hys bread beynge yet vnbleſſed prayeth for theme</p>
            <p>He ſayth alſo that they be fayth full howe then be they in daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger? If Chryſte haue redemed them, what nedeſt thou thenne nowe to praye for theyr redemp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon / Nowe after thys he be, gynneth to call vppon a great companye of. Saynctes. bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge hyme ſelfe in hande, that his morſell of breade is as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che too bee eſtemede, as the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious bloud of chryſt where yet he ſpeaketh nothynge at all of
<pb facs="tcp:3915:16"/> the Churche, lyuynge on earth, ſpecyally ſeynge there is not ſo moche as one lytle of the ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath ſhewed vs any thing of the Saynts departed thys li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe Nowe it followeth.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="canon">
               <body>
                  <p>which oblacion vouchſafe thou O God, father almyghtye. we be ſeche the to make bleſſed, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted ratefyed reaſonable &amp; acceptable, that it may be made to vs the bodye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and bloude of thy derely belouyd ſoone oure lorde Ieſus Chryſt.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Here at y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> fourth tyme the foles head maketh ablacyon and vſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>th ſuch worde as can not do hyt Conſyder ye here the contrary<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:3915:16"/> Chryſt prayeth for me to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that. I wretched ſynner. may be acceptable to hym And this, ſhameles butcher, labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth now to reconſyle the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onne to the father whych loueth him mooſt ſpecially and aboue all. Alas (I ſay) is not this I pray you extreme abhomynacyon, blaſphemy and denying of God yes truly is it. euen as though the bloude of Chryſte were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane alſo, and muſte nowe be purified by them and commited to the father. Alas this is to mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che mockage I can in no wyſe ſuffer yt ony longer the hower is come that touchethe my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcyence Let all men therfore ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ply them herto that this abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynacion may be taken away<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Nowe, here follow the woordes
<pb facs="tcp:3915:17"/> of all thynges mooſt noble and excellent, whiche alſo they haue all beſpotted wythe theyr owne fylthynes. See ye, here, howe theſe tryflers haue dryuen in thys woorde / FOR, and lefte oute the pryncypall part, that is, WHYCH IS, GEVEN FOR YOWE. Agayne, they nede not the body of Chryſte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> was delyuered ones tor all wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en they make theyr ſacryfyce. They patch to yet alſo, of theyre owne, the myſterye of faythe. where it is nothynge leſſe then the myſterye of fayth that they go aboute, Nowe, when they haue bleſſed the breade and the wyne. &amp;c. yet they offer Chryſte vp agayne and ſaye</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="canon">
               <body>
                  <head>The canon</head>
                  <p>we offer vnto thy Maieſtye of thy preſentes and gyfts a pure
<pb facs="tcp:3915:17"/> ſacryfyce a holy ſacryfice, and vnſported ſacryfice the holy bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ad of eternal lyfe and y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Cuppe of euerlaſtynge ſaluacyon On whyche vouchafe thou to loke with a mercyfull countenaunce &amp; accept it as thou dideſt vouch ſafe to accept the preſèts of thy ſeruaunt iuſt Abell y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacryfyce of our high father Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; that whyche thy hygh Preſt melchiſedech offred a holy ſacrifice an vnſpotted hofte</p>
                  <trailer rend="centerJustify">
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                     <lb/>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>☜<g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                     <lb/>☞.☞
<lb/>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                     <lb/>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>☞☞☞☞
<lb/>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                  </trailer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb facs="tcp:3915:18"/>
            <p> What abhominacion is thys, is not this to tred the bloud of Chr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yſt vnder fete when we wyll de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre God to haue this as accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table as Abels ſacryfice was is the bloude of Chryſt of no more value than to be compared with Abels oblation what offred A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels then a young lamb yf Abel by the oblacion was made rygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuous, then Chryſt dyed not for hym at all. And after thys man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner, ſhal a vyle and natural ſhe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe, be of more eſtimacyon, pryce and worthyenes then the mooſt precious bloude, of our onelie re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demer Chryſte. O good Lorde what a horryble blaſphemy ys thys what Chryſtyen herte is. able to abyd thes thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges ſo my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable and all to gyther full of deceyte and dampnatyon.
<pb facs="tcp:3915:18"/> Now I appeale you lordes and Rulers I beſeche you at the laſt yet turne hyther your eyes. The fathers of the olde Teſtament. weare as well ſaued by the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon of Chryſt, as we be as wyt neſſet Paule. Therfore they be falſe lyes whych theſe men bear in theyr Checkes. For in the oth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er place here before they ſaye it is a pure oblation and vnſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and here nowe they praye to God to take it as accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as he dyd Abels ſacryfyce. euen as thought Chryſte were iuferyour to Abell, where as he ought to beleue that, Chryſte re conſiled to the father, both Abel and all Gods elect.</p>
            <p>Wyth what face then O fylthy wormſacke wilt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> purify Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:3915:19"/> to the father, I thynke that yf God ſhuld raine doune aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunce of fyre, all ſhoulde be to litle too punyſh and purge this abhominable blaſphe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>y of theſe wredched Papyſtes, by whome Chryſt is crucifyed in theſe da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes. M. ſodry &amp; dyuers wayes and is put to death againe Oh this mooſt deteſtable Idolatry of theaſe wycked Popyſh maſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne be purged by no kynd of purgacyon. but by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eternall fyre of Hell. Oh let hym ſape y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may. For ſence the worlde was fyrſt cerated were there neuer greater blaſſhemies among all Heathen, then is in this Canon, For both i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> breadth &amp; le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth they exced Hieroboa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s Calnes, which though the king had the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> honor
<pb facs="tcp:3915:19"/> yet put they away all other I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrye, But the Calues, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented an outewarde ſhewe of Godly ſeruyce, as do in oure daies Idolaters and the curſed ꝓapyſtes. It followeth</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="canon">
               <body>
                  <head>The cannon.</head>
                  <p>O almyghty God commaunde theſe thinges to be borne vp by the handes of thy Aungell vnto thy Aulter aboue in the ſight of thy holy mayeſty.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>☞ Se here for Goddes ſake howe the Aſſe playeth the fole here. Nowe he goeth about to offer Chryſte to the father bi an Aungell whyche is vtterlye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the woorde of God, as y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pſamograph ſayth. For the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ather hath made, hym manye hondreth years a gone, to ſyt
<pb facs="tcp:3915:20"/> at hys ryght hand. But thys braynles fellowe. I magyneth that God hath ſoche an Aulter in heauen, as he ſayth maſſe vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on and ſo breketh vppon Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es office, which is the only true Preeſt yea, he beareth him ſelfe ſo importunely, &amp; goeth about too offer Chryſte, as though he hadde not offred hym ſelf al re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. If the heathen ſhuld thus of raſhnes. Vſe theyr ſacryfyce too Hilarius, or Anchus y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natione of it woulde ſeme abho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mynable ynough, too bee puny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with the euerlaſtynge fyre. Oute vpon this blyndenes out vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, And now he goeth dou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne to them that be dead and like a hare brayne entreth to the Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gement of God and taketh char<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge ouer the dead whych thynge
<pb facs="tcp:3915:20"/> the holy gooſt hath forbidden bi the holye ſcripture, and woulde that we ſhulde inquite nothyng of them And yet here the Aſſe is more frantike then euer he was Here he ſaith that they reſt with God. and yet he deſireth God, to giue them parte of the ſeat of reſte and peace. It followeth.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="canon">
               <body>
                  <head>The canon.</head>
                  <p>And gyue alſo to vs thy ſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>untes ſome part &amp; fellowſhype w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy holy Apoſtes &amp; Matris</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>☞ Now behold howe he is he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re rauyeſhed with blynde deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon, and knocketh hys Popiſh hart and calleth vppon a great nombre of Sayntes, and in the mean wyle he turneth both god and Chriſt to paſture in the feld
<pb facs="tcp:3915:21"/> of forgetfulnes / and hath no nede at al of Chryſt neyther yet beleueth that Chryſt hath alrea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye purchaſed heauen for hym. And in this he vetterlye deneith deſpiſeth &amp; forſaketh Chryſte / as thoughe he had not geuen heauen frely And becauſe thoſe dulheaded and madbrayned pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pyſtes be nothynge mouede at this therfore they often tymes lay furthe the woorkes, merites &amp; deſetes of Sayntes, as thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gh they wer of more value then the precyous death of our one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sauyoure Ieſus Chryſte. And here may ye ſe and beholde the madnes of theſe Maſmon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. The Grayfrers gaue a great ſome of money, to the piſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> they might put
<pb facs="tcp:3915:21"/> in their Idol ſaynte Fraunces amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge theſe that be here nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, O the ambycious couet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng of honour deſirous to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye. For here ſhould ſoner De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelles be regreſted, then any Sayntes, Furthermore, when the bread is conſecrated / then eateth he vp all hym ſelf alone and geueth no man parte of yt. but putteth a pece of it into the Chalyce as hought the bloude of Chryſte muſt then be puryfy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> pece or elles the bloude muſt puryfy the bread / by min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyng them to gether, All thys is but tryfflynge, and hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grund of the ſcripture. It fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth in the Canon</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="canon">
               <body>
                  <head>The canon.</head>
                  <p>Lord haue no regard to my ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes but to the fayth of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregacion,</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb facs="tcp:3915:22"/>
            <p> Of thys the blynde maſſe moungers toke theyr blodenes to inſure them ſelues, &amp; wallow at thaulter as doo the ſwyne at the trough<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and goo about to de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyre a priuate fayth to them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues in theyr hartes, and at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt thus he concludeth.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="canon">
               <body>
                  <head>The Canon</head>
                  <p>Let the obſeruaunce of my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyce pleaſe the. O holy trynyte and graunt that this ſacrifyce &amp;c.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Se I pray you how madde thys ſacryfyce monger is beco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me He goeth on ſtyll to comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Chryſte to the father. Now I beſyche you al and charge youe in goddes behalfe to try thys abbominacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and looke narou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye on ii, and ſprede it abroade,
<pb facs="tcp:3915:22"/> yf it be poſſyble through all the woorld, that the ſhame of that fylthy whore of Babylon, may be all vncouered. And praye ye to God, that he vouchſafe too ſett hys almyghty worde at ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, whiche / Alas the whyle / is wholy and all togyther hyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and kepte backe from vs &amp; hath alſo been hyddred frome our forefathers, theſe mannye hondreth yeres and al by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt deteſtable abhominacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe ſacryfyce mongers and chriſt murtheres whyche thus cruelly murther &amp; crucify Chriſt. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore I ſaye, that al houſes of Stewes whyche God hath moſt earneſtly forbydde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beroes, murthers thefts. &amp;c. are not ſo hurtfull. as is this abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minacyon of Popyſh maſſes. To conclude, I beſech al Pryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces,
<pb facs="tcp:3915:23"/> Rulers, Offycers and Iudges, depely to trye w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues, and examin this horrible blaſphemy agaynſt God. and if God ſuffre you to punyſhe any ſediciouſe rybauld. that openlye taketh a waye the honor of the Maygeſtye of God why ſholde ye not as well, and moche ſoner roote out and purge this ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homynable and Antichryſtian blaſphemye agaynſte God fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> among you. Leſt the horryble wrath of GOD. as of a fitye kyl ſhuldo be prouoked againſt your neglygence. and be aduen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged as well vpon you as vpon theſe Idolatrious Preſtes loue your god and ſett you forth his glory for to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> purpoſe ye beare the ſword, and haue authoritye
<pb facs="tcp:3915:23"/> If ye this doo, he ſhall be your Prynce and Captayne and ſhal defend you thought al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuels in hel were agaynſte you yea he ſhalbe your myghtye Champio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agaynſt death it ſelfe. And ſhal delyuer you from the Pharao, &amp; ſhal at laſt bryng you in to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> eternall conntrey whiche hath pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myſed you The gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of God euer ſtrengthen you in fayth Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer rend="centerJustify">
            <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
            <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
         </trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprynted haue at al Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes By me Hans hitprycke.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
